A Guide to the Mark Kac papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA170
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mark Kac papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1934-1986
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Kac, Mark
FA170
34.82 Cubic Feet 61 document boxes and 9 record storage boxes.
61 document boxes and 9 record storage boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Mark Kac was born in Poland in 1914. His family was forced to evacuate to Moscow following World War I. Once there, his father, who had been a professor of philosophy at the University of Leipzig, made a living tutoring students in the family's one-room apartment. Kac began studying mathematics at the early age of 5, listening in on his father's lectures. Upon returning to Poland, he was taught by a French governess as a child, learning Russian, French, Hebrew and Polish. At 15 he entered the Lycée of Krzemieniec, studying Latin and Greek as well as mathematics, physics and chemistry. He next entered the Jan Kasimir University of Lvov where he was taught by Hugo Steinhaus, was awarded a doctorate in 1937, and learned English.
In 1938 Kac came to the United States on a scholarship to Johns Hopkins University. From 1939 to 1943, Kac served as an instructor at Cornell University. From 1943, the year he became a citizen, he served as an assistant professor, being promoted to full professor in 1947. In 1961 Kac came to Rockefeller University, where he spent twenty years, after which he spent the rest of his career at the University of Southern California.
Kac pioneered the modern development of mathematical probability, in particular its applications to statistical physics. This was an introduction of probabilistic methods in number theory, which he developed along with Paul Erdös. The method of quantization now in use involves the Feynman-Kac integral, developed along with Richard Feynman. He published a classic text Statistical Independence in Probability, Analysis and Number Theory in 1959. His most famous work is a paper he wrote for the American Mathematical Monthly in 1966 titled "Can One Hear the Shape of a Drum?" For this work, Kac received the Chauvenet Prize from the Mathematical Association of America in 1968 for the most outstanding expository article on a mathematical topic. In 1978 he won the George David Birkhoff Prize in Applied Mathematics, a joint prize of the American Mathematical Society and the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics.
Arrangement note
Arranged primarily in chronological and alphabetical order.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged materials are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: correspondence, manuscripts, administrative files, notes, lectures, personal material, reprints, papers, lecture files, student work including thesis, and audio-visual materials.
Statistics; Statistical physics; Physics; Mathematics; Medical education
- Correspondence, 1940-1981; 1; 14.52 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes both personal and professional correspondence.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent's last name; some in chronological order.
  - undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1943-1960, 1 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1943-1960, 2 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1943-1960, 3 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1943-1960, 4 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1948, 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1948, 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1950s, 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1950s, 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1960s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1970s, 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1970s, 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1978-1984, 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1978-1984, 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1980s, 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1980s, 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - A, 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - A, 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ablowitz, Mark J. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Alemany, Ricardo (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Alfred Jurzykowski Foundation (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Amassian, Vahe Eugene (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - American Board of Arts and Sciences (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - American Mathematical Society, 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - American Mathematical Society, 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - American Mathematical Society, 3 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - B, 1 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - B, 2 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - B, 3 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Baclawski, Kenneth P. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Barany, George (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Barcilon, Victor (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Barrett, Wayne (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Benguria, Rafael (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Biographies and Bibliographies (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Blum, J.R. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Boehm, George (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Boltzmann Symposium (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Borowski, Zbignieu (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Brookhaven National Laboratory (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Burton, Yuri (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - C, 1 of 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - C, 2 of 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - C, 3 of 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cannon, John T. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Case, Kenneth (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Catastrophe Theory (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Catholic University of America (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chern, S.S. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chudnovsky, Gregory V., 1 of 5 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chudnovsky, Gregory V., 2 of 5 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Chudnovsky, Gregory V., 3 of 5 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Chudnovsky, Gregory V., 4 of 5 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Chudnovsky, Gregory V., 5 of 5 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Cohen, Daniel (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Cohen, E.G.D. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cole and Jaffe (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Committee of Concerned Scientists (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Conner, Howard E. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Cornell University (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Cornell Visiting Fellowship (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - D, 1 of 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - D, 2 of 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Davies, E. Brian (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Demetrius, Lloyd A., 1 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Demetrius, Lloyd A., 2 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Denmark (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Department of the Navy (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Dole, Vincent P. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Donaghey, Robert M. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Drobot, Adam Thomas (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Dyson, Freeman (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - E (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - England (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Erdös, Paul (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Eskin, Grisha (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - F, 1 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - F, 2 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - F, 3 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Farinholt, Larkin H. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Feinberg, Jerry M. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Filler, William (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Flexner Colloquium (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Fox, Ronald, 1 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Fox, Ronald, 2 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Fox, Ronald, 3 of 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - G, 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - G, 2 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Gallavotti, Giovanni (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Gates, D.J. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Gaveau, Bernard (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Geneva Conference (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - General (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "George" (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Ginn and Company (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Glickfield, Barnett W. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Ginn and Company (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Glickfield, Barnett W. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Glimm, Jim (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Grossberg, Stephen (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Grunbaum, Francisco (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Gusack, Russel (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - H, 1 of 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - H, 2 of 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Harper, Larry (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Hersh, Reuben (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Hetnarski, Bogumil (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Holsztynski, Wlodzimierz (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Hrbacek, Karel (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Humboldt Foundation (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - IBM, 1 of 2 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - IBM, 2 of 2 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Invitations (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Joint Projects Committee for Mathematics (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Institut de la Vie, 1 of 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Institut de la Vie, 2 of 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Institut de Mathématiques (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Institute of Mathematics Statistics (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - J (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Jaffe, Arthur (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Kannai, Yakar (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - K, 1 of 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - K, 2 of 2 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Kendall, David G. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Kiefer, Jack Carl (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Klein, Martin J. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Klein, William (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Knight, Bruce (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Kochen, Manfred (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Krein, Mark G. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Kripke, Saul (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - L, 1 of 3 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - L, 2 of 3 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - L, 3 of 3 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Ladik, Jr., John F. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Laks, Mitchell (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Levy, Sanford (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Lewis, John (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Liepins, Gunnar (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Lin, Ta-Feng (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Lipset (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Lowell-Putnam Examination (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Luttinger, Joaquin (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - M, 1 of 3 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - M, 2 of 3 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - M, 3 of 3 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Martin, Donald Anthony (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Martin-Lef, Anders (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Mayr, Ernst (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - MIT General (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - MIT Press (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - McArthur Foundation (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - McKean, Henry P. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - McLaughlin, David (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - McVoy, Eugene J. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Mielniczuk, Wieslaw (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Miller Institute for Basic Research in Science (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Montroll Symposium (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Muthuswamy, Bhaskav (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - N, 1 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - N, 2 of 2 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - National Academy of Science (NAS), 1 of 3 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - NAS, 2 of 3 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - NAS, 3 of 3 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - NAS Committee on Human Rights (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF), 1 of 2 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - NSF, 2 of 2 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Ndumu, Martin Ngu (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Neuroscience Research Program (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Norman, Frank (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - NATO Scientific Committee, 1 of 2 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - NATO Scientific Committee, 2 of 2 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Northwestern University (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Norton, Karl K. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - "Nut" file (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - O (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - O'Neil, Patrick E. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Onsager, Lars (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Oxford (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - P, 1 of 4 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - P, 2 of 4 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - P, 3 of 4 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - P, 4 of 4 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Pais, Abraham (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Palley, Igor (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Papanicolaou, George C. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Pending (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Personal Miscellaneous (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Petrov, Valentin V. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Pincus, Joel (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Pinsky, Mark A. (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Pittel, Boris G. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Poland (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Polish Academy of Sciences (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Polish Conference, 1 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Polish Conference, 2 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Polish Correspondence, 1 of 3 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Polish Correspondence, 2 of 3 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Polish Correspondence, 3 of 3 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Polish Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Positions (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Prigogine, Ilya (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Prohorv, Yu (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Publishers (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Putterman, Seth, 1 of 2 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Putterman, Seth, 2 of 2 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Q-R, 1 of 3 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Q-R, 2 of 3 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Q-R, 3 of 3 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Radin, Charles (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Rees, Mina (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Rice and North (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Rosenblatt, Murray (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Riordan, John (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Rosser, Barkley (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Rota, Gian-Carlo, 1 of 2 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Rota, Gian-Carlo, 2 of 2 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Rockefeller University, 1 of 2 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller University, 2 of 2 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Russian Correspondence (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - S, 1 of 3 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - S, 2 of 3 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - S, 3 of 3 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Sawyer, W.W. (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Scarsdale Teachers Association (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Schreiber, Morris (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Schwartz, Martin (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Sellers, Peter (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Seth (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - SIAM & SIMS, 1 of 2 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - SIAM & SIMS, 2 of 2 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - SIAM Board of Trustees, 1 of 2 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - SIAM Board of Trustees, 2 of 2 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - SIAM Prize (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Siegert, Arnold J.F. (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Sigma XI (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Simms, John Carson (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Singer, Isadore (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Singer, Jonathon (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Sloan Foundation, 1972 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Sloan Foundation, 1973-1974 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Sloan Foundation, 1975-1980; 1 of 3 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Sloan Foundation, 1975-1980; 2 of 3 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Sloan Foundation, 1975-1980; 3 of 3 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Sloan Science Book Committee, 1 of 2 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Sloan Science Book Committee, 2 of 2 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Smoluchowski, Marian, 1 of 2 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Smoluchowski, Marian, 2 of 2 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Smoluchowski, Roman (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Smoluchowski, Zofia (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Society for Natural Philosophy (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Springer (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Steinhaus, Hugo (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Stevens, Charles F. (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Stroock, Daniel W. (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Sylvester, Garrett Smith (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Szygowski, Juliusz (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - T, 1 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - T, 2 of 2 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Tainiter, Melvin (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Tharp, Leslie H. (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Thompson, Colin J., 1 of 3 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Thompson, Colin J., 2 of 3 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Thompson, Colin J., 3 of 3 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - "The Three-body Toda System" (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Tupitsyn, Victor (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Turner, John William (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - U-V (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Ueno, Tadashi (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Uhlenbeck, G.E., 1 of 4 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Uhlenbeck, G.E., 2 of 4 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Uhlenbeck, G.E., 3 of 4 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Uhlenbeck, G.E., 4 of 4 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Ulam, Stan, 1 of 2 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Ulam, Stan, 2 of 2 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - USSR Visa (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Universities (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Van Moerbeke, Pierre, 1 of 3 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Van Moerbeke, Pierre, 2 of 3 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Van Moerbeke, Pierre, 3 of 3 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Velocity (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - W, 1 of 3 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - W, 2 of 3 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - W, 3 of 3 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Wang, Hao (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Ward, John (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Wegrowicz, Lucjan (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Weinberg, Alvin M. (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Weizmann Institute of Science, 1 of 6 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Weizmann Institute of Science, 2 of 6 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Weizmann Institute of Science, 3 of 6 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Weizmann Institute of Science, 4 of 6 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Weizmann Institute of Science, 5 of 6 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Weizmann Institute of Science, 6 of 6 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Windwer, Stanley (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Wu, Tai Te (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - X-Y-Z, 1 of 2 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - X-Y-Z, 2 of 2 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Yale University Council Committee (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Yanenko Affair (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Zasada, Christopher S. (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Ziff, Robert (Box 33, Folder 11)
- Manuscripts, 1940-1981; 2; 1.32 Cubic Feet
  Includes early drafts of published articles; some correspondence.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by manuscript title or subject.
  - 1945-1947 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - 1975 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - "About Brownian Motion and Bound States" (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Bibliography of Multivariate Statistical Analysis (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Birkhoff's Ergodic Theorem (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Birkhoff Prize Talks, Atlanta, 1978 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Catastrophe Theory as Applied to the Social and Biological Sciences (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Computers (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Enciclopedia Italiana (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Feynman Manuscript (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Functional Integration (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Gabor Szego (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - "A Heuristic Approach to Ornstein-Zernike Theory" (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - Journals (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - Krein Volume (Box 34, Folder 15)
  - "The Making of Statistican" (Box 34, Folder 16)
  - "Marceli Stark in Memoriam" (Box 34, Folder 17)
  - "Marian Smoluchowski and the Evolution of Statistical Thought in Physics" (Box 34, Folder 18)
  - "Master Equations for Finite Systems" (Box 34, Folder 19)
  - "A Mathematical View of the Theory of Changes Phase" (Box 34, Folder 20)
  - "Mathematics: Reflections on the Present and Thoughts About the Future" (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - "Mathematics in the Physical Sciences" (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Historical Papers and Letters (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - "A Note on Eigenvalues and Eigenfunctions of the Laplace Operator" (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - One-dimensional Objects (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Papers, 1978-1981 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Polish manuscripts, 1942 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - [Probability Density] (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Pythagorean Theorem on the Surface of a Sphere (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Reviews of Kac Articles (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Scientific American Article-first draft (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Scientific American Article-revised version (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - "The Search" (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - "Some Applications of the Theory of Brownian Motion to Potential Theory" (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - "Some Remarks on the Various Ensembles Used" (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - "Statistical Analysis of a Certain Random Walk (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - "Statistical Mechanics of Some One-dimensional Systems" (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Steinhaus Manuscript (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Steinhaus' Polish Manuscripts (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Taylor Manuscripts (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - "The Themes and Trends of Mathematics" (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - "A Theory of Diffusion" (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - Von Neumann, John (Box 36, Folder 11)
- Administrative Files, 1958-1971; 3; 1.32 Cubic Feet
  Includes editorial work for professional journals and administrative work for Rockefeller University.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Appointments and Promotions (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda/Meetings (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Calendars, 1971-1975 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Calendars, 1976-1980 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - National Academy of Science (NAS) (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - NAS Editorial Board (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - NAS Exchange of Scientists USSR (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - NAS Nominations (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - NAS Report Review Committee, 1 of 2 (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - NAS Report Review Committee, 2 of 2 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - NAS "TNG in Statistical Mathematics" (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - "Nut" file (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Press, 1 of 2 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Press, 2 of 2 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller University (RU) Computer Center (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - RU Faculty Appointments (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - RU Faculty Club (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - RU General, 1973 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - RU General, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - RU General, 1975 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - RU General, 1976 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - RU General, 1977 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - RU General, 1978 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - RU General, 1979-1981 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - RU President's Office (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - RU Press (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Security (Box 39, Folder 9)
- Lecture Files, 1960-1975; 4; 1.76 Cubic Feet
  Includes transcripts of lectures, some correspondence, and notes.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by lecture title or subject.
  - Lecture notes Summer, 1995 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Notes, 1964-1965 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - 1972 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Brandeis Lectures on Phase Transitions (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Brandeis University Summer School, 1966 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Catastrophe Theory (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Chance and Regularity, Merrimack College, 1965 (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Christmas Lecture Notes (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - City University of New York, Fall, 1964 (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - "Conference on Mathematical Theory of Elementary...." (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Congress of Scholars and Scientists of Polish Background (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - Cornell University Centenary, 1965 April (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - Dog Flea Model Pictures (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Engineering College Council-Cornell University (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Ferromagnetism (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Fifth Berkeley Symposium on Mathematics (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Gas Dynamics Colloquium-Northwestern University, 1964 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - George Washington Project (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Gibbs Lecture and Related Material (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Harrelson Lectures, 1965 November 29-December 3 (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Hierarchical Model (Box 41, Folder 9)
  - Holiday Lectures, 1962 (Box 41, Folder 10)
  - Important Lectures (Box 41, Folder 11)
  - Introduction to the General Theory of Relativity (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Josiah Willard Gibbs Lecture, 1967 January 24 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Kac Lectures (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Lecture Notes on Thermodynamics (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Lectures in Probability (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Leiden, 1963 April 20 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - MAA Cooperative Summer Seminar (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Mathematics-Science Seminars Summer, 1967 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - MacMillan Company (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - MIT Conference on Information Transfer, 1965 August 2 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - NAS Symposium on Stability of Celestial Mechanics, 1967 June-July (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Notes on 1947-1948 Kac Lectures by Bill Newcomb (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Potential Theory in Three Dimensions (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Probability Theory and Differential Equations (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - "The Pythagorean Theorem on the Surface of a Sphere", 1966 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Relevance of the College Experience March 1966, 1966 March (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Rockefeller Institute Holiday Science Lectures (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Rota, G.C. (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Schedules (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Sigma XI (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - Science and Engineering Television, 1963 February 14 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - SIAM, 1960-1965; 1 of 2 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - SIAM, 1960-1965; 2 of 2 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - SIAM Meeting Courant Symposium, 1965 June (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Society for Natural Philosophy, 1966 October 21-22 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Some Interconnections between Mathematics and Other Disciplines (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Swathmore College Fall, 1965 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Towson State College Baltimore, 1966 October 26 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - University of Kentucky Centennial, 1965 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Various Notes (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Wayne State University (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Wesleyan University, 1965 February 8-13 (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Wittenberg University Address, 1966 October 13 (Box 44, Folder 12)
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1942-1964; 5; 4.84 Cubic Feet
  Includes notes of laboratory experiments.
  Arranged in chronological and in alphabetical order.